BEN GROSS

8437 Kedvale Ave, Skokie, IL 60076 (217) 972-7918 ben@nutrition.engineering

EDUCATION

Massachusetts Institute of Technology xPRO

Professional Certificate in Coding: Full Stack Development with MERN

Online December 2021

Purdue University West Lafayette, IN

MS, Food Science, Computational Science & Engineering

December 2009

University of Illinois

BS, Chemistry

Champaign-Urbana, IL May 2005

SKILLS

Back-end: Cloud Functions, App Engine, Compute Engine, Firebase, CloudSQL, Apps Script, GraphQL

APIs: Google Analytics, Authentication and reCaptcha, Stripe, SendGrid

Front-end: Angular, Bootstrap, React

WORK EXPERIENCE

Nutrition Engineering, LLC

Skokie, IL

Chief Solutions Architect

2018 - Present

- Developing business, engineering and science apps that drive innovation in academia and industry.
- Leading development of Nutrasheets, a food development and nutrition labeling add on for Google Sheets.
- Helping Google Workspace customers automate business processes and expedite workflows.
- Leveraging Google Cloud Platform to deliver web content, manage users, integrate data, and bill customers.

Morgan Consultants, Inc.

Atlanta, GA

Senior Food Scientist, Process Development Engineer

2018 - 2020

- Developed food processes from benchtop to pilot plant to manufacturing scale.
- Determined process capital scope to meet and exceed financial, food quality and food safety needs.
- Optimized food processes for both new and existing SKUs to maximize profit and quality.

Kellogg Company	Battle Creek, MI
Product Development Scientist	2015 – 2018
Associate Product Development Scientist	2013 – 2015
Assistant Product Development Scientist	2010 - 2013
Pre-professional Intern	2010

- Developed cookies, crackers, fabricated chips, extruded products and snack mixes.
- Formulated nine new retail SKUs leveraging positive nutrition and culinary trends to delight consumers.
- Partnered with marketing and finance to forecast technical and financial feasibility for innovation projects.
- Provided organization-wide subject matter expertise in cracker product development.
- Designed three new school channel SKUs that meet the USDA's stringent nutritional guidelines for the school lunch program generating in excess of \$15 MM sales.
- Developed two new SKUs for Convenience Stores generating in excess of \$5 MM sales.
- Demonstrated throughput increase and quality improvement on baking lines via product reformulation.
- Implemented a \$50MM cost savings / supply chain opportunity across multiple product lines.

Purdue University

West Lafayette, IN Research Assistant 2006-2009

Created a services-oriented software and hardware architecture that increased data throughput sixteen-fold.

- Integrated embedded network hardware and software to remotely detect 1 ppm arsenite in liquid.
- Isolated and identified microbial pathogens from food using biochemical and immunological techniques.

Tate and Lyle Company

Decatur, IL

Analytical Chemistry Intern

2002

- Calibrated process FTIR & NIR instruments for moisture analysis of corn gluten, starches and syrups.
- Developed iodometric method pertaining to propylene oxide modification of corn starches.
- Audited safety standard operating procedures for pilot plant operations.

PUBLICATIONS

Nutrasheets leverages Google Cloud Platform to deliver 4x faster access to food data Published 5-20-21 on LinkedIN

Google Cloud Powers Addition of 500+ Food Components to Nutrasheets Published 12-17-20 on LinkedIN

Nutrasheets Brings Dual-Column Nutrition Facts and Ingredient Statements to Google Sheets Published 11-18-20 on LinkedIN

Nutrasheets Adds USDA Food Data Central, Drops Google Drive, Launches in India Published 12-9-19 on LinkedIN

Nutrasheets Brings Food Formulation and Nutrition Labeling to Google Cloud Platform Published 10-31-19 on LinkedIN

WORK SAMPLES

www.nutrasheets.com

benjamingro.github.io

workspace.google.com/marketplace/app/nutrasheets/561596970235

github.com/benjamingro

PRESENTATIONS

Electrochemical-Based Whole Cell Biosensor System using Pyocyanin as a Reporter Signal Pittcon Analytical Chemistry Conference

Chicago, IL 2009

Development of a multichannel test bed for screening and distributing bioreporter-based chemical sensors Center for Food Safety Engineering Conference West Lafayette, IN 2007

Remote sensing of agricultural contaminants using biosensor networks over TCP/IP American Chemical Society Conference

Chicago, IL 2007

HIGHLIGHTS

Kellogg Moonlighting Product Development Award, 1st Place (2010, 2012, 2014)

Kellogg Push Forward Commercialization Award (2012, 2013, 2014)

Kellogg Research Quality & Technology Academy, Snacks 201, Instructor (2013 - 2015)

Kellogg International Technical Symposium, Presenter (2013)

Kellogg K-Values Formal Award Winner, 3rd Place (2012)

Purdue Graduate Student Government, Senator (2007-2008)